Guide to the miriam cooke Papers, 1981-2013 (bulk 1985-1992) UA.29.02.0257
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
miriam cooke Papers
1981-2013
Bulk 1985-1992
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Cooke, Miriam.
UA.29.02.0257
1.5 Linear Feet
miriam cooke is a professor in the Department of Asian and Middle Eastern Studies at Duke University. The miriam cooke Papers include materials documenting a faculty exchange program between Duke and Cadi Ayaad University in Morocco, as well as other projects related to Islam and the Middle East, such as the Duke Islamic Center (DISC) and a draft of the book Mediterranean Passages: Readings from Dido to Derrida (2008). The papers also include materials about Duke faculty operations, particularly within the Department of Asian and African Languages and Literature (AALL).
Arrangement
This collection is divided into three series: Professional Materials, Administrative Materials, and Publications.
Biographical / Historical
miriam cooke was born in Colorado on August 30, 1948. (cooke uses lowercase letters in her name.) She received her M.A. from the University of Edinburgh, Scotland, in 1971; and her D.Phil. from the University of Oxford, U.K., in 1980. From 1981-1987, she was assistant professor at the Duke Center for International Studies. In 1987, she joined the faculty of Duke's Department of Asian and African Languages and Literature (AALL), later known as the Department of Asian and Middle Eastern Studies. She was chair of AALL from 1996-1999 and from 2001-2004, teaching classes in Arabic language, literature, and culture. Beginning in 1985, she was instrumental in establishing an exchange program between faculty at Duke and at Cadi Ayaad University in Marrakesh, Morocco. Her many books include War's Other Voices: Women Writers on the Lebanese Civil War (1988), Women and the War Story (1997), Women Claim Islam: Creating Islamic Feminism Through Literature (2001), and Mediterranean Passages: Readings from Dido to Derrida (co-edited with Erdag Göknar and Grant Parker, 2008). cooke was a Mellon Fellow at the Gender and War Institute at Dartmouth College (1990) and was awarded two Fulbright Scholarships, which allowed her to conduct research in Lebanon and Yemen (1982) and in Syria (1995-1996). In 1983, cooke married Bruce Lawrence, fellow Duke professor and founding director of the Duke Islamic Center. As of July 2016, she is Braxton Craven Professor of Arab Cultures at Duke University and is on the executive committee of Duke's Middle East Studies Center.
Access Restrictions
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use of administrative records. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
Records, such as search committee files or others pertaining to employment where individuals are identified, are closed for 70 years.
Use of audiotapes and videotapes from this collection requires the creation of reference copies. Reference copies for some materials may have been made, and if a reference copy exists, it is noted in this finding aid. To arrange for the creation of reference copies of other items, please contact University Archives staff. Although these recordings are now stored in a stable environment, their condition and playback quality is unknown.
Provenance
The miriam cooke Papers were received by the Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, as a gift in 2016.
Related Materials
Bruce Lawrence Papers, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University. Morocco at Duke scrapbook, 1985 Sept., Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University. Miriam Cooke papers, Ms. 2014.019, Brown University Library.
Collection Overview
This collection documents the professional and administrative activities of miriam cooke, professor in the department of Asian and Middle Eastern Studies at Duke University (formerly AALL, Asian and African Languages and Literature). Professional activities documented include the development of a faculty exchange program between Duke and Cadi Ayaad University in Marrakesh, Morocco, beginning with a festival of Moroccan culture held at Duke in 1985. Several files contain correspondence with the United States Information Agency (USIA), which provided grant funding for the program, and journals from faculty members in the United States and Morocco detailing their exchange experiences. Other files in this series contain information relating the Center for Study of Muslim Networks, which formally developed into the Duke Islamic Center (DISC) in 2006; and a project on War and Gender conducted in the early 1990s with Duke University History professor Alex Roland. Administrative activities documented focus on cooke's role as a Duke professor. Files include records about faculty and courses in the AALL Department; and correspondence with three deans of Arts and Sciences at Duke: Richard White, Hans Hillerbrand, and Malcolm Gillis. Some materials relate to cooke's time on committees monitoring the interests of women faculty and non-regular faculty at Duke. Publications files include correspondence with members of the Mediterranean Study Committee, information about the Oceans Connect project between Duke and Middle Eastern faculty, and draft chapters for the book Mediterranean Passages: Readings from Dido to Derrida. Materials are largely textual, comprising correspondence, minutes and agendas, faculty travel journals, clippings, publications, and related printed matter. A VHS tape and a few photographs are also contained within the collection.
Middle East -- Study and teaching -- United States; Morocco -- Study and teaching; Islamic countries -- Study and teaching; Morocco -- Description and travel; Asian languages -- Study and teaching; Cooke, Miriam.; Duke University -- Faculty; Duke University. Trinity College of Arts and Sciences. Office of the Dean; Duke University. Duke Islamic Studies Center.; Duke University. Department of Asian and Middle Eastern Studies
- Professional Materials, 1984-1997; 1
  - Morocco Festival: Morocco Summer Program, 1984-1985 (Box 1)
  - Morocco Festival: Association of Grand Atlas Telexes, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Morocco Festival, 1985-1987 (Box 1)
  - Morocco Festival: Press Coverage, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Morocco Festival: Morocco at Duke, circa 1985 (Box 2, Video-cassette UA2902020257-VHS-0001)
  - USIA (United States Information Agency) Proposal, 1986-1990 (Box 1)
  - Moroccan Committee, 1986-1997 (Box 1)
  - Moroccan Committee: Cadi Ayaad Conference, 1992-1993 (Box 1)
  - USIA Periodical Reports, 1987-1988 (Box 1)
  - USIA Periodical Reports, 1987-1989 (Box 1)
  - USIA Periodical Reports, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - USIA Periodical Reports, 1990-1991 (Box 1)
  - USIA Periodical Reports, 1991-1994 (Box 1)
  - War and Gender Project with Alex Roland, 1990-1994 (Box 1)
- Administrative Materials, 1981-2013; 2
  - DISC - Originally "Center for Study of Muslim Networks", 2000-2001 (Box 1)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted until 2026
  - DISC - Originally "Center for Study of Muslim Networks": Consortium Meeting Oct. 4-5, 2002, 2001-2002 (Box 1)
    Restricted until 2027
  - DISC - Originally "Center for Study of Muslim Networks": Consortium Meeting, January-February 2004 (Box 1)
    Restricted until 2029
  - DISC - Originally "Center for Study of Muslim Networks", 2006 (Box 1)
    Restricted until 2031
  - DISC (Duke Islamic Studies Center), 2007-2013 (Box 1)
    Restricted until 2038
  - DISC (Duke Islamic Studies Center): Advisory Board Meeting, Nov-08 (Box 1)
    Restricted until 2033
  - AALL (Asian and African Languages and Literature), 1988, 1996-1997 (Box 1)
    Restricted until 2022
  - AALL (Asian and African Languages and Literature): Minutes and Proposals, 1987-1992 (Box 1)
  - AALL (Asian and African Languages and Literature): Meeting, Feb-99 (Box 1)
    Restricted until 2024
  - AALL (Asian and African Languages and Literature): Faculty Meetings, 1997 (Box 1)
  - AALL (Asian and African Languages and Literature), 1989-1992 (Box 1)
  - AALL (Asian and African Languages and Literature): Retreat, 1998 (Box 1)
    Restricted until 2023
  - AALL (Asian and African Languages and Literature): Asian International University, 1996 (Box 1)
    Restricted until 2021
  - AALL (Asian and African Languages and Literature), 1998 (Box 1)
  - AALL (Asian and African Languages and Literature), 1997 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Dean of Arts and Sciences: Richard White, 1981-1993 (Box 1)
    Restricted until 2063
  - Correspondence with Dean of Arts and Sciences: Hans Hillerbrand, 1985-1987, 1989-1991 (Box 1)
    Restricted until 2061
  - Correspondence with Dean of Arts and Sciences: Malcolm Gillis, 1989, 1991-1993 (Box 1)
  - Faculty Women's Network - Non-Regular Faculty, 1986-1992 (Box 1)
    Restricted until 2062
- Publications, 1997-2008; 3
  - MSG (Mediterranean Study Group), 1997-2001, 2006, 2008 (Box 1)
  - MSG (Mediterranean Study Group): Mediterranean Faculty, 1997-1998 (Box 1)
  - Mediterranean Passages - Draft (1 of 6), 2003-2004 (Box 1)
  - Mediterranean Passages - Draft (2-6 of 6), 2003-2004; 5 folders (Box 2)